Register of the August Zaleski Papers, 1919-1981
Hoover Institution Archives
- CHRONOLOGICAL FILE-I (Boxes 1-4)
  - 1942-1945 (Folder 7)
    - Three letters by unidentified persons from Rio de Janeiro to Zaleski, February 1942
    - Telegrams by the Poselstwo Rzeczypospolitej Polskiej in Bern to the Ministerstwo Spraw Zagranicznych, February-March 1942?
    - Telegram by General Sikorski to the Poselstwo Rzeczypospolitej Polskiej in Bern, 25 February 1942?
    - Report by Ropp from the Polish Information Center on American public opinion with a cover letter by the Ministerstwo Informacji i Dokumentacji to the Prezes Rady Ministrow, 3 March 1942
    - Agenda of a meeting of the Rady Ministrow in March 1942, 5 March 1942
    - Memorandum by the British Foreign Office on Polish-Soviet relations, 27 March 1942
    - Letter by Ambassador Papee to Zaleski, 3l March
    - Letters about the Komitet Redakcyjny Ksiegi Zbiorowej and about the publishing business
    - Memorandum from Michal Potulicki on Polish propaganda in America with a cover letter to Zaleski, 17 April
    - Letter by Adam Romer to the Szef Kancelarji Cywilnej Prezydenta Rzeczypospolitej Polskiej, 22 April 1942. Original
    - Letter by Minister Skarbu to the Szef Kancelarji Cywilnej Prezydenta Rzeczypospolitej Polskiej, 17 April 1942. Original
    - Letter by Zaleski to Minister Skarbu, 24 April 1942
    - Memorandum by Michal Potulicki on Allied propaganda with a cover letter to Zaleski, 9 May 1942
    - Report by the Ministerstwo Informacji i Dokumentacji on political conditions in France, 2l May 1942
    - Decree by the Prezydent Rzeczypospolitej on the Naczelne Wladze Wojskowe
    - Letter by Lord Cecil to Sir Ralph Wedgwood, Baronet, 27 May 1942
    - Letter by Zaleski to General Sikorski, 2 June 1942
    - Report on a talk between General Sikorski and Anthony Eden, 8 June 1942
    - Letter by T. Filipowicz to Lord Cecil on the Polish-Soviet border, 20 July 1942
    - Letter by Julian Mojsiewicz to Zaleski on the Middle East Polish Forces, 15 November 1942. Original
    - Proclamation by Polish underground organizations, January 1944
    - Invitation by the Prince and Grand Duchess of Luxemburg to Zaleski, 25 April 1944
    - Broadcast on the success of a Polish armoured division against two German S.S. corps, 22 August 1944
    - Letter by Hilda Dodds to Churchill on the Polish-Soviet border, 29 September 1944
    - Letter by General Kukiel to General Sikorski, 16 February 1945
    - Leaflet by British religious leaders on the necessity to protect Polish Christianity against the Soviet Union, 24 February 1945
    - Letter by the Ministerstwo Informacji i Dokumentacji to the United Nations Films Production, 3 July 1945
    - Letter by Zaleski to an archbishop on the fate of the Poles deported to the Soviet Union, 14 October 1945
    - Letter by Jadwiga Romerowa to Zaleski, 30 April 1945, and memorandum on J. Modzelewski, 30 April 1945
    - Letter by A. Zoltowski to Zaleski on the Polish Research Center in London, 21 December 1945
  - 1946 (Box 2., Folder 1)
  - 1947-1949 (Folder 2)
  - 1950-1952 (Folder 3)
  - 1953 (Folder 4)
  - 1954 (Folder 5)
  - 1955 (Folder 6)
  - 1956 (Folder 7)
  - 1957 (Folder 8)
  - 1958 (Folder 9)
  - 1959 (Folder 10)
  - 1960 (Box 3., Folder 1)
  - 1961 (Folder 2)
  - 1962 (Folder 3)
  - 1963 (Folder 4)
  - 1964 (Folder 5)
  - 1965
    - January-June (Folder 6)
    - July-December (Folder 7)
  - 1966 (Box 4., Folder 1)
  - 1967 (Folder 2)
  - 1968 (Folder 3)
  - 1969 (Folder 4)
  - 1970 (Folder 5)
  - 1971 (Folder 6)
  - 1972
    - January-April (Folder 7)
    - April-November (Folder 8)
- CORRESPONDENCE, ALPHABETICAL-I, 1949-1976 (Box 5)
  Significant correspondence of August Zaleski and Ewelina Zaleska, arranged alphabetically by correspondent.
  - Unidentified, 1951-1976 (8) (Box 5., Folder 1)
  - Argent, Ernest, 1959-1967 (5) (Folder 2)
  - Asociacion de los Estudiantes Universitarios Polakos en Espania, 1964 (1) (Folder 3)
  - Barclay, Vera, 1963 (1) (Folder 4)
  - Bartczak, Czeslaw. See Stowarzyszenie Dobroczynno Kulturalne Polakow w Brazylii
  - Beckowa, Jadwiga, 1969 (1) (Folder 5)
  - Bobkowski, Aleksandr, 1964 (1) (Folder 6)
  - Brandys, Jan, 1964-1967 (3) (Folder 7)
  - Burzak, Piotr, 1973-1975 (3) (Folder 8)
  - Butler, 1952 (1) (Folder 9)
  - Chowaniec, 1972 (1) (Folder 10)
  - Chomka, 1973 (1) (Folder 11)
  - Cienski, Witold, 1970-1971 (2) (Folder 12)
  - Czechlewski, Joseph, 1968 (1) (Folder 13)
  - Febran, Federacja Braterska Niezaleznych, 1962 (1) (Folder 14)
  - Godlewski, J., 1964 (3) (Folder 15)
  - Good, Paul, 1966 (1) (Folder 16)
  - Gordon-Watkins, Eleanor, 1964 (2) (Folder 17)
  - Grudzinska, Nina, 1964-1966 (2) (Folder 18)
  - Guenther, Wladyslaw, 1964 (1) (Folder 19)
  - Halecki, Oscar, 1964-1966 ia, 1973 (1) (Folder 20)
  - Hutten-Czapski, Emeryk, 1967 (1) (Folder 25)
  - Janiszewska, Stefania, 1974 (1) (Folder 26)
  - Jankowski, Pawel, 1964-1966 (2) (Folder 27)
  - Kolo Generalow i Pulkownikow bylych Wyzszych Dowodcow, 1964 (1) (Folder 28)
  - Koscialkowski, W., 1963 (1) (Folder 29)
  - Kwapiszewski, M., 1966 (1) (Folder 30)
  - Lawinski, Ludwik, 1970 (2) (Folder 31)
  - Lisicki, Adolf. See Febran, Federacja Braterska Niezaleznych
  - Litwinski, Leon, 1964-1966 (6) (Folder 32)
  - Lyczak, Adam. See Polish National Fund
  - Makohonski, Aleksandr, 1970 (l) (Folder 33)
  - Mikoszewska, Maria. See Mikoszewski, Zbignew
  - Mikoszewski, Zbignew, 1967 (1) (Folder 34)
  - Miszczakowa, E., 1962 (1) (Folder 35)
  - Mostwin, Danuta, 1964 (1) (Folder 36)
  - Niekraszowa, Stefania, 1968-1971 (8) (Folder 37)
  - Noel-Stanton, Halina, 1972 (1) (Folder 38)
  - Okoniewska, Jadwiga, 1964-1966 (4) (Folder 39)
  - Okulicz, Kazimierz, 1956-1969 (3) (Folder 40)
  - Paige, Roy, 1953-1963 (2) (Folder 41)
  - Paschalska, M., 1953 (1) (Folder 42)
  - Polish Musicians Abroad. See Niekraszowa, Stefania
  - Polish National Fund, Inc., New York, 1964-1966 (3) (Folder 43)
  - Polonia, Towarzystwo, 1970 (1) (Folder 44)
  - Procopieni, Czeslaw, 1963 (1) (Folder 45)
  - Potulicka, Helena, 1964-1969 (6) (Folder 46)
  - Powierza, Wladyslaw, 1969-1970 (2) (Folder 47)
  - Roman, Jerzy, 1949-1975 (6) (Folder 48)
  - Sawicki, K. See Kolo Generalow i Pulkownikow Bylych Wyzszych Dowodcow
  - Sienkiewicz, Kazimierz. See Polonia, Towarzystwo
  - Skarbek, Stanislaw, 1969 (3) (Folder 49)
  - Skarbkowa, Zofia. See Skarbek, Stanislaw
  - Skogholm, Carl Werner, 1963 (1) (Folder 50)
  - Sokolnicki, J., 1967-1970 (2) (Folder 51)
  - Stowarzyszenie Dobroczynno-Kulturalne Polakow w Brazylji, 1963 (1) (Folder 52)
  - Strzalkowski, Wieslaw, 1970-1972 (2) (Folder 53)
  - Szlachetkowa, Olimpia, 1964-1967 (2) (Folder 54)
  - Tokarzewski-Karaszewicz, Michal, 1963 (1) (Folder 55)
  - Vincent, A. K., 1966 (2) (Folder 56)
  - Walczak, T. F., 1972-1975 (3) (Folder 57)
  - Wardok, St. See Associacion de los Estudiantes Universitarios Polakos en Espania
  - Wariwoda?, Mieceslaw, 1973-1974 (4) (Folder 58)
  - Wendorff, 1964 (2) (Folder 59)
  - Wieniawa Zubrzycka, Halina, 1968 (1) (Folder 60)
  - Zagloba, 1964 (2) (Folder 61)
  - Zaleska, E., 1969 (1) (Folder 62)
  - Zawisza, K., 1969 (3) (Folder 63)
  - Zawodny, Janusz, 1968-1969 (2) (Folder 64)
- CORRESPONDENCE, CHRONOLOGICAL-I, 1940-1977 (Box 6)
  Less significant correspondence of August Zaleski and Ewelina Zaleska, arranged chronologically.
  - Undated (22) (Box 6., Folder 1)
  - 1940 (1) (Folder 2)
  - 1947 (2) (Folder 3)
  - 1951 (1) (Folder 4)
  - 1952 (3) (Folder 5)
  - 1953 (1) (Folder 6)
  - 1954 (1) (Folder 7)
  - 1955 (4) (Folder 8)
  - 1956 (1) (Folder 9)
  - 1958 (3) (Folder 10)
  - 1959 (5) (Folder 11)
  - 1961 (1) (Folder 12)
  - 1962 (1) (Folder 13)
  - 1963 (8) (Folder 14)
  - 1964 (33) (Folder 15)
  - 1965 (2) (Folder 16)
  - 1966 (12) (Folder 17)
  - 1967 (13) (Folder 18)
  - 1968 (19) (Folder 19)
  - 1969 (30) (Folder 20)
  - 1970 (31) (Folder 21)
  - 1971 (10) (Folder 22)
  - 1972 (15) (Folder 23)
  - 1973 (6) (Folder 24)
  - 1974 (8) (Folder 25)
  - 1975 (2) (Folder 26)
  - 1976 (11) (Folder 27)
  - 1977 (2) (Folder 28)
- GREETING CARDS-I, 1949-1977 (Boxes 7-12)
  Greeting cards and congratulatory letters and telegrams, arranged chronologically.
  - Undated (Box 7., Folder 1)
  - 1949 (Folder 2)
  - 1950 (Folder 3)
  - 1952 (Folder 4)
  - 1953 (Folder 5)
  - 1954 (Folder 6)
  - 1955 (Folder 7)
  - 1957 (Folder 8)
  - 1958 (Folder 9)
  - 1959 (Folder 10)
  - 1961 (Folder 11)
  - 1962 (Folder 12)
  - 1963 (Folder 13)
  - 1964 (Folder 14)
  - 1965 (Folder 15)
  - 1966 (Folder 16)
  - 1966 (Box 8., Folder 1-5)
  - 1967 (Box 9., Folder 1-5)
  - 1967 (Box 10., Folder 1)
  - 1968 (Folder 2-4)
  - 1969 (Folder 5-6)
  - 1969 (Box 11., Folder 1-2)
  - 1970 (Folder 3-4)
  - 1971 (Folder 5)
  - 1972 (Folder 6)
  - 1972 (Box 12., Folder 1)
  - 1973 (Folder 2-3)
  - 1974 (Folder 4-5)
  - 1975 (Folder 6)
  - 1976 (Folder 7)
  - 1977 (Folder 8)
- SUBJECT FILE, 1936-1976 (Box 13)
  Calling cards, cartoons, clippings, correspondence, financial records, notes, printed matter, receipts, arranged alphabetically by subject.
  - General
    - Calling cards (Box 13., Folder 1)
    - Clippings (Folder 2)
    - Financial records (Folder 3)
    - Notes (Folder 4)
    - Printed matter (Folder 5)
    - Receipts (Folder 6)
  - American Academy of Political Science (Folder 7)
  - Ambasada Rzeczypospolitej, Vatican. Serwis Informacyjny (Folder 8)
  - Anglo-Polish Conservative Society (Folder 9)
  - Association de Psychologie de Langue Française -- IX Session d'Etudes. List of participants (Folder 10)
  - Balet Legat. See Nicolaeva Legat, Nadine
  - Big Jackpot (Game) (Folder 11)
  - Chelsea School of Art (Folder 12)
  - Children and Families World Community Chest (Folder 13)
  - Chowanna, 15 July 1973 (Folder 14)
  - De Courcy, Kenneth, Trial of (Folder 15)
  - Dziennik Polski (Folder 16)
  - Fawley Court, Divine Mercy College (Folder 17)
  - Free China Newsletter, 13 February 1964 (Folder 18)
  - Godlewska, Anna. See Prix Anna Godlewska d'Amitié Polono-Suisse
  - Hartman (Folder 19)
  - Institut Historyczny Imienia Generala Sikorskiego (Folder 20)
  - Kleczkowski, S. (Folder 21)
  - Klub Dyskusyjny, London (Folder 22)
  - Kolo Lwowian, London (Folder 23)
  - Londyn, Kolo Wiedzy Wojskowej (Folder 24)
  - Nicolaeva Legat, Nadine (Folder 25)
  - Polish church (Folder 26)
  - Polish culture outside of Poland (Folder 27)
  - Polish politicians. Cartoons (Folder 28)
  - Polska Agencja Telegraficzna (Folder 29)
  - Prix Anna Godlewska d'Amitié Polono-Suisse (Folder 30)
  - Rada Rzeczypospolitej Polskiej. List of candidates (Folder 31)
  - Simon Community Trust (Folder 32)
  - Sino-British Cultural Association and Friends of Free China Association (Folder 33)
  - White, Berry and Catford, London (Folder 34)
  - Wladislaus Quintus (Society?) (Folder 35)
  - Zagraniczny Komitet Odbudowy Zamku Krolewskiego w Warszawie (Folder 36)
  - Zjednoczenie Osadnikow Polskich w Afryce Poludniowej (Folder 37)
  - Zurawski, Antoni (Folder 38)
  - Zwiazek Ziem Wschodnich Rzeczypospolitej Polskiej (Folder 39)
- BIOGRAPHICAL FILE-I, 1947-1980 (Box 13)
  Article, book, chart, arranged alphabetically by author or subject.
  - Mackiewicz, St., "August Zaleski -- Prezydent Rzeczypospolitej Polskiej", 1947. Typed copy (Box 13., Folder 40)
  - Wandycz, Piotr, August Zalesk i, Paris, 1980 (Folder 41)
  - Zaleski family. Genealogical chart (Folder 42)
- WRITINGS-I, 1919?-1960 (Box 14)
  Holographs and typed copies of articles by Zaleski, arranged by Zaleski's naval aide-de-camp Mariusz B. Hrynkiewicz-Moczulski; each folder contains a detailed inventory of the contents of that folder prepared by Hrynkiewicz-Moczulski.
  - "Memoirs." Typed copy (Box 14., Folder 1)
  - "Rozne sa tego powodu...," December 1931. Holograph and typed copy (Folder 2)
  - "Wicher," June 1931. Holograph and typed copy
  - "Podczas mego urzedowania jako M.S.Z...," 1932? Holograph and typed copy
  - "W chwili wybuchu pierwszej wojny...," n.d. Holograph and typed copy
  - "Kazdy Polak, ktory zajmuje sie...," n.d. Holograph and typed copy
  - "Ni w Piec Ni w Dziewiec," 1960. Holograph and typed copy
  - "Z dniem 1-ego Stycznia 1926...," January 1926. Holograph and typed copy
  - "Przypisy do 'Wspomnien'," Chapter 1, October 1949; Chapter II-IV, n.d. Holograph and typed copy (Folder 3)
  - "Berthelot opisal mi pobyt w Berline...," 2 October 1931. Holograph and typed copy
  - "Czesto slyszymy nawolywanie...," June 1941? Holograph and typed copy
  - "Dnia 6-ego Grudnia 1944r. bylem na sniadaniu z O`Malley`m w Oxford and Cambridge Clubie," December 1944. Holograph and typed copy
  - "Jako drugi, juz posredni powod...," n.d. Holograph and typed copy
  - "Przeprowadzilem z Briandem...," September 1928. Holograph and typed copy
  - "Lord Cushindun powiedzial mi...," September 1928. Holograph and typed copy
  - "W zwiazku z artykulem Kajetana Morawskiego...," February 1957. Holograph and typed copy
  - "W zalaczeniu znajdziesz kopje 2-ch dokumentow...," n.d. Holograph and typed copy
  - "Jozef Pilsudski a Alianci w Czasie 1-ej Wojny Swiatowej," April 1963. Holograph and typed copy
  - "Moj drogi, W poniedzialek bedziesz mial ten list," 1919? Holograph and typed copy
  - "Moj drogi, naturalnie, ze gdyby mnie pan Paderewski...," 1919? Holograph and typed copy
  - "Kopia czesci listu do Litwinskiego," 1966. Holograph
  - "Wspomnienia Prezydenta A. Zaleskiego z Okazji 50-Lecia Niepodleglosci Polski," 1968. Typed copy
Container List, Part II
- GENERAL, 1927-1974 (Box 15)
  Clippings, correspondence, memoranda, reports.
  - Inventory of Part II by M. B. Hrynkiewicz-Moczulski (Box 15., Folder 1)
  - Jankowski, Pawel. Correspondence and notes of P. Jankowski, 1953-1974 (Folder 2)
  - Ministerstwo Spraw Zagranicznych. Handwritten and typed memoranda and reports of the ministry, 1927-1941. Some documents composed by August Zaleski (Folder 3)
  - World War II. Mimeographed, printed, and typewritten documents relating to World War II, 1939-1940. See also Ministerstwo Spraw Zagranicznych
    - General. Includes inventory of the documents compiled by M. B. Hrynkiewicz-Moczulski (Folder 4)
    - "Polish Territory Occupied by the Germans," n.d. (Folder 5)
- BIOGRAPHICAL FILE-II, 1940-1980 (Boxes 15-17)
  Clippings, financial and medical records, membership cards, arranged alphabetically by subject.
  - General
    - Clippings re August Zaleski (Box 15., Folder 6-7)
    - Clippings re August Zaleski (Box 16., Folder 1-3)
    - Financial records, medical records, membership cards
      - Undated (Folder 4)
      - 1940-1949 (Folder 5)
      - 1950-1959 (Folder 6)
      - 1960-1969 (Folder 7)
      - 1970-1979 (Box 17., Folder 1)
      - 1980 (Folder 2)
  - Property of August Zaleski confiscated by the Schutzstaffel during World War II. Handwritten and typed notes, lists of confiscated items (Folder 3)
- CHRONOLOGICAL FILE-II, 1922-1982 (Boxes 17-20)
  Clippings, correspondence, memoranda, notes, reports.
  - Undated (Box 17., Folder 4-8)
  - Undated (Box 18., Folder 1-3)
  - 1922-1923 (Folder 4)
  - 1932-1939 (Folder 5)
  - 1940 (Folder 6)
  - 1941 (Folder 7)
  - 1942 (Folder 8)
  - 1943 (Folder 9)
  - 1944 (Folder 10)
  - 1945 (Folder 11)
  - 1946 (Folder 12)
  - 1947 (Folder 13)
  - 1948 (Folder 14)
  - 1949 (Folder 15)
  - 1950 (Box 19., Folder 1)
  - 1951 (Folder 2)
  - 1952 (Folder 3)
  - 1953 (Folder 4)
  - 1954 (Folder 5)
  - 1955 (Folder 6)
  - 1956 (Folder 7)
  - 1957 (Folder 8)
  - 1958 (Folder 9)
  - 1959 (Folder 10)
  - 1960 (Folder 11)
  - 1961 (Folder 12)
  - 1962 (Folder 13)
  - 1963 (Folder 14)
  - 1964 (Folder 15)
  - 1964 (Box 20., Folder 1)
  - 1965 (Folder 2)
  - 1966 (Folder 3)
  - 1967 (Folder 4)
  - 1968 (Folder 5)
  - 1969 (Folder 6)
  - 1970 (Folder 7)
  - 1971 (Folder 8)
  - 1972 (Folder 9)
  - 1973 (Folder 10)
  - 1974 (Folder 11)
  - 1975 (Folder 12)
  - 1976 (Folder 13)
  - 1977 (Folder 14)
  - 1978 (Folder 15)
  - 1979 (Folder 16)
  - 1980 (Folder 17)
  - 1981 (Folder 18)
  - 1982 (Folder 19)
- CORRESPONDENCE, ALPHABETICAL-II, 1938-1972 (Boxes 21-23)
  Arranged alphabetically by correspondent.
  - Inventory of the series compiled by M. B. Hrynkiewicz-Moczulski (Box 21., Folder 1)
  - Antropus, Lady Olive (13), 1957-1972 (Folder 2)
  - Apostolic Delegation (9), 1967-1970 (Folder 3)
  - Arciszewki, Miroslaw, 1954 (Folder 4)
  - Babinski, Waclaw, 1949 (Folder 5)
  - Bobkowski, Aleksander, 1955 (Folder 6)
  - Brzeski, Tadeusz (8), 1954 (Folder 7)
  - Bugayski, Tadeusz (16), 1954-1967 (Folder 8)
  - Chrzanowski, Leon, 1940 (Folder 9)
  - Ciechanowski, Jan (18), 1941-1969 (Folder 10)
  - Dolanowski, W., 1947 (Folder 11)
  - Eden, Anthony, n.d. (Folder 12)
  - FitzGibbon, Louis (7), 1970-1976 (Folder 13)
  - FitzGibbon, Madeleine. See FitzGibbon, Louis
  - Gawronski, W. (4), 1966 (Folder 14)
  - Glazer, Michal (11), 1940-1957 (Folder 15)
  - Godlewski, J. (27), 1954-1968 (Folder 16)
  - Grubinski, Waclaw (15), 1954-1970 (Folder 17)
  - Grzybowski, W. (3), 1943-1949 (Folder 18)
  - Guenther, Wl. (4), 1957-1963 (Folder 19)
  - Halecki, Oskar (4), 1966-1971 (Folder 20)
  - Holinski, Alfred (10), 1955-1967 (Folder 21)
  - Kaczkowska, Ada, 1955. Includes typescript reminiscences re Roman Knoll (Folder 22)
  - Karszo-Siedlewski, J., 1951 (Folder 23)
  - Kniaziolucki, Leon (4), 1955-1970 (Folder 24)
  - Kobylecki, Eugeniusz, 1967 (Folder 25)
  - Korsak, W. R., 1955 (Folder 26)
  - Koscialkowski, Waclaw (23), 1940-1972 (Folder 27)
  - Kot, Stanislaw, 1940 (Folder 28)
  - Kupferwasser, L. A. (109), 1955-1970 (Folder 29)
  - Kwapiszewskii, M., 1951-1965 (Folder 30)
  - Lipski, J. (5), 1953 (Folder 31)
  - Litwinski, Leon (135), 1938-1969. Includes typewritten and printed copies of L. Litwinski's writings and also clippings from French newspapers re Poland, Eastern Europe, Soviet Union, and world politics (Folder 32-34)
  - Litwinski, Leon (Box 22., Folder 1-3)
  - Lubodziecki, Stanislaw (3), 1971 (Folder 4)
  - Lepkowski, S., n.d. (Folder 5)
  - Lukasievicz, J., 1950 (Folder 6)
  - Lyczak, Adam (42), 1952-1972 (Folder 7)
  - Mackiewicz, Stanislaw (10), 1951-1955 (Folder 8)
  - Mazurkiewicz, W., 1956 (Folder 9)
  - Modrzewski, Stanislaw (5), 1953 (Folder 10)
  - Morawski, Kajetan (2), 1955 (Folder 11)
  - Odzierzynski, Roman, 1951 (Folder 12)
  - Okulicz, K. (7), 1965-1972 (Folder 13)
  - Pojak, Antoni (11), 1957 (Folder 14)
  - Potworowski, Gustaw (8), 1940-1941 (Folder 15)
  - Pruszynski, Czeslaw (8), 1954-1964 (Folder 16)
  - Rozanski, E.C., 1965 (Folder 17)
  - Rubin, Wl., Bishop, 1971 (Folder 18)
  - Sapieha, Adam, Prince (3), 1950 (Folder 19)
  - Sapieha, Eustachy, Prince (11), 1954 (Folder 20)
  - Sosnkowski, Kazimierz (2), 1947-1952 (Folder 21)
  - Stowarzyszenie Lotnikow Polskikh (7), 1965-1970 (Folder 22)
  - Szumlakowski, Marian (31), 1940-1965 (Box 23., Folder 1)
  - Szygowski, Juliusz (8), 1955-1972 (Folder 2)
  - Tatarkiewicz, Teresa. See Tatarkiewicz, Wladyslaw
  - Tatarkiewicz, Wladyslaw (7), 1967-1972 (Folder 3)
  - Vincent, A. K. (10), 1966-1967 (Folder 4)
  - Walczak, Tadeusz (6), 1971-1972 (Folder 5)
  - Wendorff, Bohdan (8), 1959-1967 (Folder 6)
  - Wszelaki, Jan, 1948 (Folder 7)
  - Zamoyski, Stefan, Count (6), 1963-1967 (Folder 8)
  - Zawisza, Aleksander (18), 1955-1971 (Folder 9)
- CORRESPONDENCE OF AUGUST ZALESKI AND EWELINA ZALESKA WITH RELATIVES AND FRIENDS, 1933-1981 (Boxes 23-24, 30)
  - Inventory of the series compiled by M. B. Hrynkiewicz-Moczulski (Box 23., Folder 10)
  - Chlapowski, Andrzej (2), 1941-1952 (Folder 11)
  - Cybulska, Zofia, 1948 (Folder 12)
  - Elmore, Mary (11), 1957-1966 (Folder 13)
  - Falter, Alfred (3), 1940-1950 (Folder 14)
  - Komorowska, Helena. See Komorowski, Henryk and Zoltowska, Helena
  - Komorowska, Henryka, 1946 (Folder 15)
  - Komorowski, Henryk (2), 1957-1976 (Folder 16)
  - Korsak, Anita. See Korsak, Witold
  - Korsak, Witold (22), 1950-1966 (Folder 17)
  - Mrozowski, Stanislaw, 1939 (Folder 18)
  - Obligado, Hector Rafael, 1972 (Folder 19)
  - Obligado, Rebeca Elvira. See Obligado, Hector Rafael
  - Ostolska, Wanda, 1950 (Folder 20)
  - Potworowska, Magdalena, 1952 (Folder 21)
  - Potworowski, Gustaw, 1944 (Folder 22)
  - Roman, Jagienka. See Roman, Jerzy
  - Roman, Jerzy (17), 1948-1978 (Folder 23)
  - Zaleska, Ellionor (7), 1948-1969 (Box 24., Folder 1)
  - Zaleska, Halina. See Zaleski, Juliusz
  - Zaleska, Maria (2), 1966 (Folder 2)
  - Zaleska, Sofia (9), 1950-1957 (Folder 3)
  - Zaleski, Juliusz (8), 1952-1959 (Folder 4)
  - Zaleski, Michal (10), 1940-1952 (Folder 5)
  - Zaleski, Szczesny (4), 1948-1949 (Folder 6)
  - Zaleski, Xawery, 1944 (Folder 7)
  - Zoltowska, Helena (22), 1961-1968 (Folder 8)
  - Zoltowski, Zbigniew (31), 1957-1972 (Folder 9)
  - Correspondence of August Zaleski and Ewelina Zaleska with Maria Weintraub and Jan Zoltowski (Box 30)
    Correspondence of August Zaleski and Ewelina Zaleska with Maria Ewelina Weintraub and Jan Zoltowski, arranged alphabetically by type of correspondence and therein by name of correspondent.
- CORRESPONDENCE, CHRONOLOGICAL-II, 1944-1971 (Box 24)
  - Inventory of the series compiled by M. B. Hrynkiewicz-Moczulski (Box 24., Folder 10)
  - 1944-1957 (Folder 11)
  - 1958-1971 (Folder 12)
- DIARIES AND NOTES OF EWELINA ZALESKA, 1940-1971 (Boxes 25-26)
  Arranged chronologically.
  - Undated (Box 24., Folder 13)
  - 1940 (Box 25., Folder 1)
  - 1941 (Folder 2)
  - 1942 (Folder 3)
  - 1943 (Folder 4)
  - 1953 (Folder 5)
  - 1967 (Folder 6)
  - 1971 (Box 26., Folder 1)
- GREETINGS CARDS-II, 1942-1981 (Boxes 26-27)
  - Undated (Box 26., Folder 2-4)
  - 1942-1957 (Folder 5)
  - 1960-1969 (Folder 6)
  - 1970-1972 (Folder 7)
  - 1975-1977 (Folder 8)
  - 1978 (Box 27., Folder 1)
  - 1979 (Folder 2)
  - 1980-1981 (Folder 3)
- WRITINGS-II, 1942-1964 (Boxes 27-28)
  Circular letters, fragments, memoirs, notes, arranged alphabetically by form of the document.
  - Circular letters, fragments, notes. The authorship of some compositions is uncertain (Box 27., Folder 4)
  - Memoirs
    - Inventory of the memoirs' chapters compiled by M. B. Hrynkiewicz-Moczulski (Folder 5)
    - Complete draft. Typescript unless otherwise indicated
      - Chapters I-V (Folder 6)
      - Chapters VI-VII (Folder 7)
      - Chapters VIII-IX. Handwritten copy (Folder 8)
    - Incomplete drafts. Holographs (Box 28., Folder 1-9)
- OVERSIZE FILE, 1949-1971 (Box 29)
  Greetings cards, membership certificate, arranged alphabetically by form of the document.
  - Greeting cards (Box 29., Folder 1)
  - Membership certificate (Folder 2)
- AUDIO-VISUAL FILE, undated
  - Photographs, undated; (19 prints / 1 envelope (Folder Photo file, 80163 - 10A-V)
    11 prints depicting relatives and friends of August Zaleski, 4 prints depicting the grave of August Zaleski, 2 prints depicting August Zaleski as a Foreign Minister, 1 print depicting Polish War Cemetery, and 1 print depicting Polish Museum.